<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Academic</title>
    <link>https://alexander-belikov.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://alexander-belikov.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>Alexander Belikov, CR</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://alexander-belikov.github.io/images/icon_huf49b158b2681d286a60137da38ca7574_154815_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://alexander-belikov.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://alexander-belikov.github.io/post/2021-wos-arango/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://alexander-belikov.github.io/post/2021-wos-arango/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;wos&#34;&gt;WOS&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you choose to use a graph database, such as ArangoDB, over something SQL-like for your dataset of interest? How to cast Web of Science into a graph schema?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We live in an era of accelerating data generation. The sizes of datasets keep growing and so does their structure. Despite the continuously growing capacity of computers real-world datasets surpass the limits of in-memory processing of even larger commercially available computers, and so data manipulation and analysis has to be aided by the use of databases. Across multiple domains, notably sociology, most interesting phenomena tend to have graph structure rather than tabular structure.
Graph databases, compared to their more established SQL counterparts offer multiple advantages, due to a more natural representation of the data. Instead of tables, where each row contains a record with potentially empty fields, in graph databases, entities are vertices and the relations between them are represented by edges. A well-known join operation is mathematically represented as a reaching second order neighbours.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
